Guide to the Hatheway family papers, 1788-[ca. 1900]
Hatheway family papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Hatheway family papers, 1788-[ca. 1900]
2281
Hatheway family.
4.6 cubic ft.
Correspondence, militia records, financial records, speeches, essays, and scrapbooks.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers relating to the family, personal affairs, and political career of Samuel Gilbert Hatheway (1780-1867).
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Samuel Gilbert Hatheway (or Hathaway, 1780-1867), a native of Bristol County, Massachusetts, moved to New York State in 1803. He was a justice of the peace from 1810-1858; served as a member of the State Assembly in 1814 and 1818 (from Cortland County; served in the State Senate in 1822; was a major general in the New York Militia, 1823-1858; was elected to Congress as a Democrat in 1833; was a presidential elector on the Democratic ticket of Pierce and Ring, 1852; and was a delegate to the Democratic National Convention in 1860. His son, Samuel Gilbert Hatheway, Jr. (1810-1864) was a lawyer, state legislator, and Union Army officer of Elmira, New York.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence relating to family matters, presidential elections (1832-52), New York politics, and chartering of banks; commissions, certificates, petitions, orders, and other records of the New York State Militia, 19th Division; and bills and receipts of Samuel Gilbert Hatheway; personal and professional correspondence, speeches, and military records of Samuel Gilbert Hatheway Jr., including letters (1858-59) from Francis A. Roe describing political unrest in Italy; correspondence, military papers, and memorabilia of Major John Shadrach Hatheway, 1st Artillery Regiment, relating chiefly to his Mexican War service and his command of Columbia Barracks, Fort Vancouver, Oregon Territory; student letters, essays and other papers of George Rodney Hatheway; papers of Calvin Luther Hatheway of Solon, New York, relating to his business interests, militia service, state and local politics, and Democratic Party strife (1860); correspondence of Sarah Hatheway Whitney and her husband Dr. Benajah T. Whitney, including letters from Clarksville, Tennessee, concerning social life and slavery, and from California (1850-51); correspondence and scrapbooks of Elizabeth Dorothea Hatheway relating to her studies, her teaching activities in the antebellum South, her travels in Europe, and current affairs; and miscellaneous letters and papers of Hiram Hooker Bickford, Caroline Boyd, Lavinia Mathilda Hatheway, Shadrach Hatheway (fl. 1788), and Welthea Hannah (Hatheway) Boyd.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Hatheway family.; Bickford, Hiram Hooker.; Boyd, Caroline, 1848-1882.; Boyd, Welthea Hannah Hatheway, 1817-1855.; Hatheway, Calvin Luther, 1821-1885.; Hatheway, Elizabeth Dorothea, 1823-1908.; Hatheway, George Rodney, 1815-1839.; Hatheway, John Shadrach, 1813-1853.; Hatheway, Lavinia Mathilda, 1819-1885.; Hatheway, Samuel Gilbert, 1780-1867.; Hatheway, Shadrach.; Roe, Francis A.; Whitney, Benajah T.; Whitney, Sarah Hatheway, 1811-1872.; Democratic Party (U.S.); New York (State).Legislature.; New York (State).Militia.; United States.Army.; United States.Congress.House.
Subjects:
Banks and banking.; Commerce.; Education.; Slavery.; Voyages and travel.; Women teachers.
Places:
Clarkville (Tenn.)--Social life and customs.; Europe--Description and travel.; Italy--Politics and government.; New York (State)--Politics and government.; Oregon.; United States--Politics and government.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Mexican War, 1846-1848.
Form and Genre Terms:
Essays.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Family Genealogy (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letterbook Indexes (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1788 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1799 -1819 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1820-1822 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1823 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 1824, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 1826-1828 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 1829 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 1830 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Addresses ca. 1831 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 1831, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Jan.-Aug., 1833 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Sept.-Dec., 1833 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Jan., 1834 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Feb.-Mar., 1834 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Apr., May, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- June-Oct., 1834 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Dec., 1834 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- 1835 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 1836 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- 1837 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- 1838, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- 1840-1842 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 1843, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- 1845 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- 1846 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- 1847 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- 1848 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- 1849 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Jan.-May, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- June-Dec., 1850 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Jan.-May, 1851 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- June-Dec., 1851 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Jan.-July, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Aug.-Dec., 1852 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Jan.-Mar., 1853 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Apr.-June, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- July-Dec., 1853 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Jan.-May, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- June-Dec., 1854 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- 1855 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- 1856 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- 1857 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- 1858, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- I860, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- 1862 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- 1863 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- 1864 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- 1865-1867 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- 1868-1870 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- 1870, 1871 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- 1872, 1873 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- 1874, 1875 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- 1876, 1877 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- 1878, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- 1880, 1881 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- 1882 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- 1883-1887 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- 1892, 1894-1896, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Misc. undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Family newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 13)
- News clippings (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Pamphlets: Cadets of the U.S. Military Academy, 1833; Blackstone Monument, 1855; Border Ruffian Code in Kansas, 1856; James Buchanan, His Doctrines and Policy, 1856; Hypocrisy of Black Republicans, 1856 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Ms. vol. small brown book of newspaper clippings re. the establishment of a government for the territory of Kansas, ca. 1850 (Box 5)
- Hard bound pamphlet "Proceedings of the College of Presidential Electors of the State of New York, 1876. Calvin L. Hatheway". (Box 5)
- Ms. vol. "In Memorium" Hatheway Family Album. (Box 5)
- Ms. vol. Large red-leather bound "Scrap Album" - Colonial history memorabilia; clippings of western scenery, n.d. (Box 5)
- Ms. vol. Green bound "Scrap book" of Elizabeth Hatheway of Solon, New York (I) Portraits of literary figures, musicians, English members of Parliament, and English royalty. n.d. (Box 5)
- Ms. vol. Dark greenish-grey "Scrap Book" of Elizabeth Hatheway of Solon, New York. misc. views of English landscape, literary figures, Spain, France, the East, Dickens illustrations. n.d. (Box 5)
- Hand-written copy textbook produced by some duplicating process. Textbook of John S. Hatheway, West Point, June 1, 1836 - "Outlines of the course of Civil Engineering". (Box 6)
- Ms. vol. Grey-covered binders of sermons copied by Elizabeth Hatheway; approximately 1000 sheets, n.d. (Box 6)
- Ms. vol. Green leather-bound scrapbook of Elizabeth Hatheway of Solon, New York (II) clippings, masterpieces, views of Egypt, colored plates of birds and fish, n.d. (Box 6)
- Ms. vol. Green leather-bound scrapbook of Elizabeth Hatheway of Solon, New York (IV) photos of Italian masterpieces of sculpture and painting. (Box 6)
- Ms. vol. Black-bound scrapbook of Elizabeth Hatheway (VI) "A thing of shreds and patches". Includes Confederate bond, bills, timetables, original watercolors. (Box 6)
- Ms. vol. Black-bound with red cover scrapbook - catalog illustrations and prints of flowers, n.d. (Box 6)
- Ms. vol. Black and gray bound notebook of poems, some newsclippings. Elizabeth Hatheway, Solon, July 20, 1850 (Box 6)
- Scrapbook from H.H. Bickford's private library. (Box 7)
- Brown leather bound photograph album with gold fastenings (Box 7)
- Light brown leather bound photograph album with gold fastenings (Box 7)
- Black leather bound photograph album - European scenes and native costumes (Box 7)
- Black leather bound photograph album of paintings, sculpture, and European scenes (Box 7)
- Red bound album with brass clasps. Photos of famous literary, scientific and historical figures. (Box 7)